A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Jerry A. Danzig, Series 13 FA360
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Jerry A. Danzig, Series 13
1964-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
Danzig, Jerry A.
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
FA360
1.9 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 13
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in three subseries:
Subseries 1 - Executive Chamber, 1964-1965 Subseries 2 - Subject Files, 1964-1971 Subseries 3 - Miscellaneous, 1964-1973
Biographical/Historical note
Jerry A. Danzig was born in New York, New York, in 1913. He graduated from the Horace Mann School for Boys in New York and earned a Bachelor of Arts degree from Dartmouth in 1934. He served in a variety of management and executive positions for broadcasting companies in New York City, including radio stations WOR and WINS, and network television stations CBS and NBC. In 1961, Danzig served as a television and radio consultant to the New York Republican City Committee. In 1962, he became Special Assistant to the Governor for Radio and Television, a position he held until 1973. Danzig's responsibilities included the production and distribution of radio and television commercials, or spots, for Rockefeller's gubernatorial and presidential campaigns. In 1973, Rockefeller appointed Danzig to the New York State Commission on Cable Television, on which he served until 1981. Danzig was a partner in Chester Burger & Co., a management consulting firm, from 1976 until 1985, when he became a consultant to the National Executive Service Corps.
Scope and Contents note
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains the office files of Jerry A. Danzig They document official activities in the execution of his duties as a member of Nelson A. Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is specifically addressed to or from Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document addressed to him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This series covers the majority of Jerry Danzig's service as Nelson Rockefeller's Special Assistant to the Governor for Radio and Television, from 1964 to 1973. The files consist of Danzig's internal memoranda and correspondence regarding Governor Rockefeller's radio and television appearances; bills and invoices for the production, distribution, and broadcast of television promotions; and budgets and expense accounts for programs. There are also scripts and transcripts of short promotional films on Rockefeller. Additional Danzig material is also located in the New York Office series of the Nelson Rockefeller Gubernatorial Papers (III 15 22.3). While the material in this series is primarily New York State related, the material in the New York Office series deals primarily with the 1964 Presidential Campaign.
Related Archival Materials note
See also Series 22 - New York Office, Subseries 3 - Special Assistant to the Governor for Radio and Television, for additional information on Jerry Danzig and the 1964 Presidential Campaign.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Economics; Civil service -- New York (State); Civil service; Civil defense -- United States; Civil defense; Arms control -- United States; Arms control; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); Public relations; Public policy; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Federal government -- United States; Political campaigns -- United States; New York (State); Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political science; Human rights; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; International relations; International economic relations; Latin America; International relations -- United States; New York (N.Y.); Legislation -- New York (State); State governments -- United States; United States; Vice-Presidents -- United States
- "Executive Chamber", 1964-1965; 1; 1 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries covers the eight television programs produced and shown throughout New York State on a variety of issues. The shows usually featured Governor Rockefeller and other state officials discussing a particular topic.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Additional "Executive Chamber" material can be found in the Gene Wyckoff Files series of the Nelson A. Rockefeller, Gubernatorial Papers (III 15 36).
  - Awards (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence on the submission of "Executive Chamber" broadcasts for awards.
  - Budget Scheduling (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence concerning the broadcast of 'The State Has A Budget, Too' "Executive Chamber" program.
  - Budget Show (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Transcript (2 copies) of "Executive Chamber" #4, 'The View from the Governor's Chair,' January 1965.
  - Budget Publicity (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Press release, correspondence on "Executive Chamber #4."
  - Critics (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Press lists, correspondence, memoranda on event to invite members of the media to view an "Executive Chamber" broadcast with NAR, February 1965.
  - Education (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence and memoranda on broadcast of "Executive Chamber #1," 'How Much Education'; transcripts and press releases of program.
  - "Everytown" - General Information (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Memoranda on the taping of "Executive Chamber" #8.
  - "Everytown" - Publicity (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Press release, 'sound bite' for "Executive Chamber" #8.
  - "Everytown" - Scheduling (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Correspondence and scheduling lists of planned broadcasts of "Executive Chamber" #8.
  - Initial Station Letters (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Correspondence with New York State television stations requesting time to broadcast the "Executive Chamber" programs.
  - Kinescopes on Loan (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Correspondence with Danzig to individuals who had requested copies of "Executive Chamber" programs.
  - "Little Drops of Water" - Remake Shortened Version on Pollution (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Typescript notes for NAR's opening remarks for Water Pollution episode (#2) of "Executive Chamber".
  - Mail (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Selected correspondence on "Executive Chamber" programs addressed to NAR.
  - Mailing Instructions (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Lists of stations and procedures on delivery of "Executive Chamber" tapes to stations for broadcast.
  - Memos to Mr. Flores (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Memoranda from Danzig on costs associated with the taping of "Executive Chamber" programs.
  - Message (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Memorandum to NAR from Danzig on taping of "Executive Chamber" #3, 'Legislative Preview' to be taped in the Assembly Chamber, December 1964.
  - Message Production (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Correspondence and memoranda on the taping of "Executive Chamber" #3. Transcript and notes for the program.
  - Message Publicity (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Memoranda on promoting of "Executive Chamber" #3.
  - Message Schedules and Shipping (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Correspondence and scheduling lists of planned broadcasts of "Executive Chamber" #3.
  - Miscellaneous Bills, Education Show - Budget (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Not Without Hope" - Publicity (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Correspondence and memoranda on taping of "Executive Chamber" #5, 'Not Without Hope' (program on mental retardation). Transcripts of program.
  - "The Troubled Mind" - Scheduling (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Correspondence and scheduling lists of planned broadcasts of "Executive Chamber" #7 (program on mental illness).
  - Production Education Show (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Background materials used on "Executive Chamber" #1.
  - Ratings (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Reports from the American Research Bureau on numbers of people who tuned in to "Executive Chamber" broadcasts.
  - Schedule (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Schedule of taping dates for "Executive Chamber" programs.
  - Station Managers - Mansion Invitation (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Correspondence with station managers, extending invitation to Governor's Mansion to watch a broadcast of "Executive Chamber" with NAR.
  - Talent and Personnel (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Correspondence from Danzig to selected individuals asking to join "Executive Chamber" staff.
  - "Transportation Tangle" - General Information (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Shooting schedule and transcript of "Executive Chamber" #6, 'The Transportation Tangle,' broadcast in March 1965.
  - "Transportation Tangle" - Publicity (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Correspondence and memoranda after the broadcast of "Executive Chamber" #6.
  - "Transportation Tangle" - Schedules (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Correspondence and scheduling lists of planned broadcasts of "Executive Chamber" #6.
  - "The Troubled Mind" - General Information (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Press release, shooting schedule and transcript of "Executive Chamber" #7, 'The Troubled Mind,' broadcast in April 1965. The topic was mental illness and the progress of New York State hospitals.
  - "The Troubled Mind" - Publicity (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Correspondence and memoranda after the broadcast of "Executive Chamber" #7.
  - "The Troubled Mind" - Scheduling (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Correspondence and scheduling lists of planned broadcasts of "Executive Chamber" #7.
  - Tune-in Ads (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Newspaper clippings promoting the "Executive Chamber" program.
  - "Walk in the Glen" - Replay Information (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Transcript of final "Executive Chamber" program #8, a profile of Watkins Glen, New York, to show a small community and its problems and achievements. Memoranda requesting a rerun of show.
  - Water (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Notes and transcript of "Executive Chamber #2: Little Drops of Water," broadcast in December 1964.
  - Water Production (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Shooting instructions and production guide for "Executive Chamber" #2.
  - Water Publicity (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Correspondence and memoranda regarding "Executive Chamber" #8.
  - Water Scheduling and Shipping (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Correspondence and scheduling lists for planned broadcasts of "Executive Chamber" #2.
- Subject Files, 1964-1971; 2; 0.4 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 2 is arranged alphabetically.
  This subseries covers a broad range of general topics from nearly the entire tenure of Danzig's service as Special Assistant. Of particular note in this subseries are two folders. The first is Folder 48, which contains information on the creation of the New York State Lottery System. Danzig's role in determining the proper boundaries in promoting the lottery on television can be seen. The second folder of note is Folder 41, which contains a transcript of "The Extremists," a political program produced for the 1964 California Republican Presidential Primary. The program was never aired, at Governor Rockefeller's request. This folder also has a copy of an article from a San Francisco newspaper on the program and the effect it might have had on the outcome of the primary, won by Arizona Senator Barry Goldwater, who went on to win the Republican nomination for president in 1964.
  - Albany - New York Radio-TV Facilities (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Correspondence and memoranda on installation of television and radio equipment for NAR offices.
  - "The Extremists" (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Transcript of political program prepared for the 1964 California Republican Presidential Primary and never aired. Clipping of San Francisco "News Chronicle" column by Guy Wright on the controversial program and what its effect might have been. Correspondence to broadcasters asking for return of tape.
  - Film Clips, 1965 Adirondack Horseback Trip (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Notes on production and broadcast of NAR horseback ride in Adirondacks, October 1965.
  - Film Clips, 1966, Ebenezer Baptist Church, United Nations Hammarsjkold Memorial, Manhattan State Hospital (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Notes on production and broadcast of NAR appearances at New York City events, October-November 1965.
  - Film Clips, 1965-1966, Narcotics and Highway Safety (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Notes on production and broadcast of NAR promotional spots on issues of Narcotics and Highway Safety, issued in conjunction with Annual Message to the Legislature, December-January 1965-1966.
  - Interviews, 1965-1971 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Transcripts of NAR appearances on news programs, interviews conducted in NAR.
  - Interviews, 1965-1971 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Interviews, 1965-1971 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Lottery, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases, clippings on creation of New York State Lottery system. Danzig memoranda on promotion of lottery on television and radio, including broadcasting of drawings.
  - Memorandums, NAR, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Danzig memos to NAR on various television/radio issues.
  - Memorandums, Staff, General, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Danzig memos to NAR staff on various television/radio issues, broadcasts of political events of interest to NAR.
  - Miscellaneous "Executive Chamber" Items, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Clippings, including plates for newspaper presses of "Executive Chamber" promotional articles; press releases on programs.
  - New York State Legislators Spot, "Our State Legislature" (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Program notes, taping instructions, transcript for program on New York State Legislature, October 1964.
  - New York Traffic Council - Spots - Radio and TV, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    Notes and scripts for NAR Public Service Announcements on safety during holiday travel.
  - Proposition I, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    Bills and invoices, announcements and press releases, correspondence and memoranda on the 1965 Pure Waters Bond Act, put to the voters in November 1965.
  - Radio - Governor's Mailbag, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    Correspondence and memoranda from Danzig to New York State radio station executives on program wherein Governor Rockefeller would answer citizen's mail on the radio.
  - Tape - Governor Rockefeller and the 1965 Legislature (Box 4, Folder 56)
    Transcripts, schedules, press releases, background information on NAR program "Governor Rockefeller Reviews the 1965 Legislature."
  - Tapes - Water Pollution and Traffic Safety, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    Taping schedules for NAR Public Service Announcement (PSA) spots.
  - Transcripts, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    Transcripts and press releases on NAR appearances on political programs such as "Issues and Answers" (ABC), "Face the Nation" (CBS), and "Today" (NBC), as well as local news programs throughout New York State.
  - Transcripts, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - The Truth About Medical Assistance Tape - State Network Feed, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    Schedules, press releases about NAR television appearance to discuss New York State Medical Assistance Program.
- Miscellaneous, 1964-1973; 3; 0.4 Cubic Feet
  This subseries is a melange of materials. Most prominent are the three folders of correspondence on the logistics of Governor Rockefeller's "town meetings." These were a series of open meetings across the state with community leaders and the public of specific New York counties. These community relations efforts were often filmed for local airing. Also featured in this subseries are materials on "The Nelson Rockefeller Story," filmed for the 1964 Presidential campaign.
  - Town Meetings, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    Notes, scheduling, distribution lists, memoranda and correspondence on Town Meetings held around New York State.
  - Town Meetings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Town Meetings, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - "Governor Rockefeller Goes to the People", December 1967 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    Correspondence and memoranda on program. Scheduling spots, advertisements for program.
  - Latin American Trips #1-4 and Telestar Broadcast for #3 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    Press releases on 1969 Presidential Mission to Latin America; schedules for satellite broadcasts to United States from Latin America.
  - Tapes and Film - General Information: Inquiries, Requests, Lent Out, Plans, Ideas, etc., 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    Memoranda and correspondence on individuals or broadcast outlets seeking tapes of NAR appearances.
  - Film: "The Nelson Rockefeller Story" (Box 5, Folder 67)
    Background materials, scripts, notes, production schedules for "The Nelson Rockefeller Story," created and produced for the 1964 Presidential campaign. The working title was "Rockefeller: Portrait of a Man."
  - Upstate Television Panel Tapings and Luncheons, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    Transcripts and press releases on NAR appearances and interviews with New York State outlets.